<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-11T10:30:26+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">MOBILE ROBOTICS PRACTICES</title><entry><title type="html">P2 Follow Line</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/30/p2-follow-line.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="P2 Follow Line" /><published>2024-09-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/30/p2-follow-line</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/30/p2-follow-line.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="description">Description</h2>
<p>El objetivo de esta practica es realizar un sigue linea que complete el circuito el menor tiempo posible. En este caso, el coche de formula 1 sigue una linea de color rojo y</p>

<h2 id="hardware">Hardware</h2>

<p>En esta practica contamos con un coche de formula 1 con camara para seguir la linea.
Por lo que el sensor es la camara y los actuadores son los motores del coche de formula 1.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
    <img src="/assets/images/p2/Captura desde 2024-10-11 10-03-10.png" alt="HSV" style="width: 300px" />
</div>

<h2 id="software">Software</h2>

<h3 id="filtrado-de-color">Filtrado de color</h3>

<div style="text-align: center;">
    <img src="/assets/images/p2/gyuw4.png" alt="HSV" style="width: 500px" />
</div>

<h3 id="estrategia-1">Estrategia 1</h3>
<p>Mi primera estrategia fue coger un bounfing box de la imagen y contar cuántos píxeles rojos hay tanto en la izquierda como en la derecha. La diferencia de ambos sería el error de nuestro sistema.
Sin embargo, este algoritmo no era preciso ni robusto, ya que no tenía en cuenta por ejemplo en las curvas donde tanto a izquierda como derecha tenía el mismo número de píxeles.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
    <img src="/assets/images/p2/Captura desde 2024-10-11 09-34-36.png" alt="HSV" style="width: 300px" />
</div>

<p>Como esta solución no era valida, decide incrementar el bounding box, cosa que tampoco resulto. Incluso decidi tomar la imagen entera pero seguia sin funcionar por el mismo problema.</p>

<h3 id="estrategia-2">Estrategia 2</h3>

<p>Mi segunda estrategia</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
    <img src="/assets/images/p2/Captura desde 2024-10-10 17-11-46.png" alt="dibujo" style="width: 500px" />
</div>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Description El objetivo de esta practica es realizar un sigue linea que complete el circuito el menor tiempo posible. En este caso, el coche de formula 1 sigue una linea de color rojo y]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">P1 Vacuum Cleaner</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/16/p1-vacuum-cleaner.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="P1 Vacuum Cleaner" /><published>2024-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/09/16/p1-vacuum-cleaner</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/09/16/p1-vacuum-cleaner.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="description">Description</h2>
<p> 
The goal is to develop a software for a vacuum cleaner robot. The robot must explore the most surface of the house.
For that, we only have the laser sensor and the bumper; therefore the software for this application is not quite difficult.</p>

<p>Remember that the vacuum cleaner cannot make use of localization algorithms.</p>

<p> </p>
<h2 id="hardware">Hardware</h2>

<div style="text-align: center;">
    <img src="/assets/images/Captura desde 2024-09-27 15-52-32.png" alt="Aspiradora Robot" />
</div>
<p> </p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>As actuators, we have the wheels of the robot, which can move in a linear and angular way.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>As sensors, we have a laser LIDAR 180º and a bumper.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p> </p>
<h2 id="software">Software</h2>
<p> 
The system must be reactive, so that I have developed a state machine whose behavior is described below.
 </p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
    <img src="/assets/images/p1-vacuum-cleaner.drawio.png" alt="Aspiradora Robot" />
</div>
<p> 
As you can see, my solution to the problem is a reactive and random algorithm, in which the movements in the “Turn” and “Forward” states are random. However, when the robot collides and activates the bumper state, it first moves slightly backward and then has two options. One is “Turn max angle”, which, as the name suggests, uses the laser to find the direction with the greatest detected distance and turns towards it accordingly. The other option is “Turn half angle”, where the robot rotates on its axis and changes direction by turning approximately 180º.</p>

<h3 id="videos">Videos</h3>
<p> 
In this video, you can see the robot’s operation. The video is at 4x speed, so it will appear accelerated.
 </p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
    <video width="600" controls="">
      <source src="/assets/videos/Video-completo.webm" type="video/webm" />
      Tu navegador no soporta la reproducción de videos.
    </video>
</div>
<p> 
In this other video, you can see how the robot exits the room, avoiding getting trapped inside it.</p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
    <video width="400" controls="">
      <source src="/assets/videos/Video-habitaci%C3%B3n.webm" type="video/webm" />
      Tu navegador no soporta la reproducción de videos.
    </video>
</div>
<p> </p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>At first, when the practice was presented to us, I thought about creating complex software using geometric shapes that would cover the largest possible area. However, in reality, developing complex software to perform these tasks did not seem appropriate for this practice, as we had to develop a reactive algorithm. Therefore, I ultimately opted for a random algorithm that provides random movements and is constantly checking the sensors, which is where the reactivity comes from. This resulted in a simple algorithm for a sensory cleaning robot.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Description   The goal is to develop a software for a vacuum cleaner robot. The robot must explore the most surface of the house. For that, we only have the laser sensor and the bumper; therefore the software for this application is not quite difficult.]]></summary></entry></feed>